Okay, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. So today's דף daf is כ"ח, Chaf-Chet,
we're sort of at the bottom of כ"ח, Chaf-Chet, so we'll hopefully
get about a half a דף daf ahead, so we'll be able
to finish on Sunday, and we pick up in the middle of
כ"ח עמוד א', Chaf-Chet Amud Aleph, ובשעת הגתות נאמנים על התרומה. U-visheat
hagitot ne'emanim al ha-trumah. So now we are starting to get to,
יישר כוח, Yasher Koach, we are starting to get to ways in
which times at which the עמי הארץ Ammei Haaretz are believed and
these distinctions are done away with, and one of them is in
יהודה Yehudah they're believed about קודש, Kodesh, only in יהודה Yehudah because
it's near the בית המקדש, Beis Ha-mikdash, and then in all places
they're believed about תרומה Trumah at the time of the pressing of
the grapes and of the olives. Partly רש"י Rashi says it's based
on certain facts on the ground, that people, because it was the
beginning of a whole season, everybody went and took all their vessels
to the מקוה mikvah and so on, so there was a greater
assumption that everybody was doing it in טהרה. Taharah. And also as
רש"י Rashi is going to say in a little bit, because otherwise
you would be excluding כהנים Kohanim from the ability to get all
this תרומה, Trumah, כהנים Kohanim who are חברים. Chaverim. So there's a
certain
social policy in place, particularly from the perspective of the חברים Chaverim
to ensure that this would be a time where you could believe
people. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: ובשעת הגתות נאמנים על
התרומה. U-visheat hagitot ne'emanim al ha-trumah. ורמינהי, U-ramini, I'll ask you on
this: הגומר זיתיו ישייר קופה אחת ויתננה לעני כהן, Ha-gomer zeisav yeshayir
kupa achas ve-yitnena le-ani kohen, that somebody who finishes
his pressing his olives should leave over
one basket of unpressed olives and give it to a poor כהן
Kohen who in parentheses is a חבר. Chaver. What does it mean?
Why shouldn't he press the olives? Because unpressed olives don't have liquid
come in contact with them and are not susceptible for becoming טמא.
tamei. So basically what it's saying is, here you are an עם
הארץ, Am Haaretz, you want to give your תרומה trumah to a
כהן kohen who's a חבר, chaver, here's the advice. The advice is,
don't give it after it's become olive oil, after it's become grape
juice or pre-fermented wine, give it to them in the form of
olives and grapes before it's come in contact with liquid and then
it won't be susceptible for טומאה, tumah, right? But okay, and then
they'll be able to accept it. So anyway the upshot is, is
that you're not believed on טומאה וטהרה tumah ve-taharah even at the
time of the pressing of the olives and the grapes. So the
גמרא Gemara says: אמר רב נחמן לא קשיא הא בחרפי הא באפלי.
Amar Rav Nachman lo kashya ha be-charfi ha be-afli. Depends whether we're
dealing with early or late. If basically we're dealing here with that
this was a late harvest of the olives, and therefore when you
were getting around to pressing it, it was no longer the normal
season of pressing and therefore it was a time period when you
would not be believed, you the עם הארץ. Am Haaretz. But that's
an exception, it's not a general rule. אמר ליה רב אדא בר
אבא כגון מאי? Amar lei Rav Adda bar Abba kegon mai? What
would be an example? כגון אותן של בית אביך, Kegon oson shel
Beis Avicha, like your father's, your father's house, I presume he had
an olive orchard and his stuff always ripens late and his stuff
always is ready for pressing after the time of the pressing. Okay,
that's one answer. רב יוסף אמרי בגליל לא שנו. Rav Yosef amrei
be-Galil lo shanu. We're talking about in the גליל. Galilee. Now to
say it's בגליל לא שנו, be-Galil lo shanu, that is interesting. It
means that even on the issue of תרומה trumah and the time
of oil pressing of the pressing, there's a difference between Judea and
the גליל. Galilee. Now we understood before why they made a difference
for קודש Kodesh because only in Judea were they able to get
to the בית המקדש, Beis Ha-mikdash, so there was a different context
for the aspects of קודש Kodesh than in the גליל. Galil. But
why by תרומה trumah should it make a difference? So let's see
what the גמרא Gemara says about this.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this: מתיב אביי, Meisiv Abaye, אביי
Abaye asked on this, we have a ברייתא. braisa. עבר הירדן והגליל
הרי הן כיהודה לתרומה. Ever ha-Yarden ve-ha-Galil harei hen ke-Yehudah le-trumah. נאמנים
על
היין בשעת היין ועל השמן בשעת השמן. Ne'emanim al ha-yayin bish'as ha-yayin
ve-al ha-shemen bish'as ha-shemen.
They're believed that the wine is טהור tahor when it's at the
time of pressing wine and that the oil is טהור tahor when
it's at the time of pressing oil. ולא על היין בשעת השמן
ולא על השמן בשעת היין. Ve-lo al ha-yayin bish'as ha-shemen ve-lo al
ha-shemen bish'as ha-yayin.
But not when it's the pressing season for the other thing. But
when it's their own pressing season, people are believed to say it's
טהור tahor for
תרומה trumah even in the גליל. Galilee. אלא מחוורתא כדישני מעיקרא. Ella
machvarta kedi-shani me-ikara.
The first answer was better, it was an exception, it wasn't exactly
the normal season, that's why it was a problem. But the clear
principle here is that this belief that everybody is believed about תרומה
trumah at the time of pressing is regardless of geographical location. Okay,
so here we have that in addition to the idea of believability
by קודש kodesh in general. Do, good to see you back. You
doing okay? Okay. All right. So,
in addition to believability by קודש kodesh in general, there's a believability
around תרומה trumah in all locations at the time that it's being
pressed, at the time when it's most urgent to be believed about
it. עברו הגתות והבדידים, Avru hagitot ve-habadidim, now this time passes over,
והביא לו חבית של יין לא יקבלנו.
ve-heivi lo chavis shel yayin
lo yekabelenu.
And an עם הארץ Am Haaretz brings to a חבר chaver a
barrel of wine, he shouldn't accept it.
like ten months from now at the next time of the pressing
season and then I'll be able to believe you. Even though it's
the exact same barrel. We're going to see something just like this
coming up later also.
Wouldn't he just have more opportunity to become טמא? tamei?
Well, that is a good point. So it's an excellent point actually.
Okay, so בעי מיניה רב ששת, Ba'ei minei Rav Sheshes, they asked
רב ששת...
Rav Sheshes... abstracted into a formality.
Exactly. Exactly. עבר וקיבלה מהו שיניחנו לגת הבאה? Avar v'kiblah mahu she'yanichennu
l'gas haba'ah? Let's say the כהן חבר Kohen Chaver accepted the barrel
of wine or oil and he didn't say bring it back to
me. So is he now allowed to hold onto it for until
the next pressing season and then say now, oh here it is
now ten months from now, oh yeah ten months ago the guy
told me it was טהור, tahor, now I can believe him? And
then he can make it טהור? tahor? So can he hold onto
it and then it'll change its status? אמר להו, Amar lehu, so
he said to them, תנינא, Tneina, we taught it. חבר ועם הארץ
Chaver v'Am ha'Aretz שירשו את אביהם. sheyarshu es avihen.
So now what happened is the following. A חבר ועם הארץ Chaver
v'Am ha'Aretz both had their father passed away, and their father was
עם הארץ, Am ha'Aretz, their father himself was an עם הארץ. Am
ha'Aretz. So their father left behind all of these wine and grapes
and olives and grain and all this stuff. The problem is is
that because he was an עם הארץ, Am ha'Aretz, a חבר Chaver
would have to assume that all of that is טמא. tamei. Okay?
Now you have his sons, one of them actually went ahead and
became a חבר. Chaver. The other one remained an עם הארץ. Am
ha'Aretz. All right. So what is their story? Now you could say,
okay, whatever, so you split it up and you deal with it.
Well maybe there's stuff that's actually טהור tahor that has never become
in contact with liquid and maybe that's the stuff that the חבר
Chaver wants, not the stuff that, you know, so I'll take the
dry stuff, you take the stuff that's come in contact with liquid.
So here's the problem. The problem is that if you say that
we are like equal partners in everything, then if I take the
dry grain and you take the grain that's been washed, what effectively
we're doing is we're saying I will give you my half of
the washed grain for your half of the dry grain. So basically,
I am now giving you, the עם הארץ, Am ha'Aretz, stuff that
is טמא tamei in order to take the stuff that's טהור. tahor.
I'm not allowed to do that as a חבר Chaver because I'm
basically leading you into sin. I am actually giving you stuff that's
טמא tamei that I know that you're not going to be careful
about observing the restrictions about it. So a חבר Chaver is not
allowed to give an עם הארץ Am ha'Aretz something that is already,
you know, has is already טמא. tamei.
But we're partners in this, I'm not giving you anything, I'm just
taking.
No, but effectively we're fifty percent owners in everything, so we really
should split everything down the middle. But where you're saying I'd rather
take the dry stuff and you take the washed stuff, well then
it's actually we're swapping our portions for the dry for the wet.
So that's a problem.
You could just as easily say I'll take this as oppose to
say you give me this.
No,
but legally what's happening is, but there is a way in which
it could be seen like it's just the natural way of splitting,
which is if it is the same מין, min, the same type
of thing that we're splitting. So let's take a look at that.
Okay. So let's take a look. Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So יכול לומר לו, Yachol lomar lo, you can say to him,
טול אתה חטים שבמקום פלוני ואני חטים שבמקום פלוני. Tol atta chitin
shebimkom ploni v'ani chitin shebimkom ploni. You take the wheat grain over
there and I'll take the wheat grain over here. It happens to
be the one I'm giving you is the stuff that's been washed
and the one I'm taking is the stuff that's dry. או טול
אתה יין שבמקום פלוני ואני יין שבמקום פלוני. O tol atta yayin
shebimkom ploni v'ani yayin shebimkom ploni. Or you take the wine over
there and I'll take the wine over here. Exactly how the wine
is not a problem is not exactly clear to me, but okay.
Somehow it's in a context where you know as the חבר Chaver
that the wine in a certain place was processed in a way
that was totally okay. אבל לא יאמר לו, Aval lo yomar lo,
טול אתה לח ואני יבש. tol atta lach v'ani yavesh.
Within the same grain I can't say to you, you know what,
you just take the wet grain, the stuff that's been sort of
washed and I'll take the dry one. טול אתה חטין ואני שעורין.
Tol atta chitin v'ani se'orin. Or you take the wheat and I'll
take the barley, because something like wheat and barley is clearly we're
switching our portions. Interesting thing is even the prior stuff, even if
it's all wheat and wheat, if I specifically designate well you take
the washed wheat and I'll take the dry, that still seems like
I'm switching my portion for you. But if it's relatively arbitrary, you
take the stuff half of the stuff is in one field and
half is in the other field, you know let's just you just
take the stuff over there, I'll take the stuff here, then that's
just okay, that's just a way of dividing, it's not swapping. And
this is on the principle of like יש ברירה, yesh bereira, that
if it's that if it's a logical natural division then we can
say that well that was the stuff that was always going to
be yours and his was the stuff that was always going to
be his and there was no swapping that took place. If it's
what we would consider to be a natural way of dividing it.
But if it's there's more of a sense of no, no, actually,
I'd rather, you know, some type of a sense of exchanging my
part in this for your part in that, then that's seen as
an actual sense of, you know, giving you the the טמא tamei
stuff and me taking the טהור tahor stuff, and that would be
a problem because of a type of ולפני עור.
v'lifnei iver. Is he really doing that? What?
In a sense... yeah, in effect, it is doing that. It's always
doing that, but the question is when do we have to sort
of legally see it that way, right? When do we just see
it as like a division? You know, you had to split it
somehow, so this is the, this is the... there's no swapping. When
do we see it as a split and when do we see
it as a swapping of my portion for your portion? Now you're
right, if we say אין ברירה, ein brira, we always see it
as a swapping, because then there's never a predetermined portion which is
mine or yours. But if we say יש ברירה, yesh brira, then
it means that when it's a natural type of a division, we
can see it like this was always your part and that was
always his part. But when it's a less natural type of a
division, then we see it as an exchange. Okay. All right. התניא
לן, ha-tanya lan, now we talked on this, אותו חבר שורף הלח
ומניח את היבש. oto chaver soref ha-lach u-maniach et ha-yavesh. So this
חבר, chaver, that if he's a כהן, kohen, okay,
and he basically gets, you know, gets stuff that is has come
in contact with liquid or actually is liquid, but now let's say
הלח ha-lach in the case over there, like the washed grain. So
what can he do with this? So it's תרומה טמאה. teruma tmea.
So he's not allowed to eat תרומה טמאה. teruma tmea. The only
thing you can do with תרומה טמאה teruma tmea is that you
burn it. ומניח את היבש, u-maniach et ha-yavesh, but he doesn't have
to worry about the stuff that's never been in contact with liquid
because that's טהור. tahor. All right. Now אמאי, amai, now here's the
key question. Why, if it worked out that he took, you know,
he had to take the... you know, he had to split it
down the middle and he had to take stuff that he had
to assume was טמא tamei that had been washed, why does he
have to burn it? יניחנו לגת הבאה? yanichenu le-gat ha-ba'a? Why not
just wait until the next pressing time, right? And then he'll be
able to believe that it was טהור. tahor. Now the interesting thing
is, the person who actually knows it's טמא tamei or could make
that claim is dead, right, the father died. But the interesting thing
is, it sounds like you don't even need somebody to make a
claim. It just seems to be like at the time of the
pressing, we can just assume that everything is טהור. tahor. Right, we
can just assume everything is טהור tahor at the time of pressing.
So you don't even have to get the father to come back,
and you know, so if the reality is that you can just
assume at that time, even stuff that's already come into your possession,
then why doesn't he just wait around?
Wait, if you know something was pressed not at the... no, no,
it's just right.
Right. Oh, you mean... oh, you mean if it's pressed not at
the season and...
oh, he knows how, how formalized?
Right. That's an interesting question too. Right, we are dealing with it
was pressed during the season but wasn't delivered until can you sort
of wait around until the next time? Right. You're saying let's say
it wasn't pressed... well, I think that was the phrase before by
the לטי עלה, latei ala, right, where the case of the לטי
עלה latei ala it seemed that he didn't have another alternative. So
it seems that minimally it does have to have been pressed during
the right season, that at least there's maybe some facts that support
it. So let's see what the גמרא'ס Gemara's answer is. אמאי יניחנו
לגת הבאה? amai yanichenu le-gat ha-ba'a? So the גמרא Gemara says בדבר
שאין לו גת. bidvar she-ein lo gat. No, maybe it's a type
of thing that there's no season for pressing, right? Who knows what
it is? It's some type of thing, you know, maybe anyway it's
grain and it's washing of a grain and maybe this whole thing...
first of all, it's not clear that this applies to stuff that's
not olive oil and grapes, right, which has a very particular season
and you gather it all together and there's a very limited time
that everybody's working on pressing it and so on. Something like grain,
obviously there's seasons for grain but it does not have the same
type of a focused period, and maybe it wasn't the same reality.
So anyway there's not even any evidence it applies to non-olive and
grapes and it wouldn't apply to something that did not have a
pressing season.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says ויניחנו לרגל? v'yanichenu le-regel? Okay. But
we're about to learn that everybody's also believed on the רגל regel
that the תרומה teruma is טהור. tahor. Okay, and maybe again you
don't have to ask anybody, you can just assume everything is טהור
tahor even and you just wait until the רגל. regel. So בדבר
שאינו משתמר לרגל. bidvar she-eino mishtamer le-regel. All right. It's something that
will spoil. Okay. So we don't have any evidence from that that
it says destroy it, that it means there's no options. Maybe in
theory there are options if you wait for the גת gat or
you wait for the רגל, regel, but we'd be talking in a
scenario where that's not available. So we don't have an answer to
the question of if you've actually already received it and therefore had
to assume it's טמא, tamei, maybe you just wait until the right
time and then can assume it's טהור. tahor. Okay. And presumably once
you assume it's טהור, tahor, it doesn't become טמא tamei again. Meaning
once
it gets a stamp of טהור, tahor, it remains that way. So
it is pretty formalist, yes.
Very broad application of the idea of
נאמנות על הרגל. ne'emanut al ha-regel. Right, נאמנות ne'emanut about, well, if
it's the רגל, regel, people know that they're supposed to be טהור.
tahor. So something he's eating on the רגל regel you can assume
is טהור. tahor. But you know, six months ago when he was
preparing them, he was processing it...
right, so that's an excellent point and that gets exactly to this
issue that how much is it based on the real facts of
people's care and how much is it based on certain policy concerns
that when you get to the bottom... In terms of technical הלכה,
Halacha, we would believe people, all of these are stringencies upon stringencies
and we waive them because of שמחה. Simcha. Exactly, and we'll see
that the רגל Regel point is not so much based on the
issue of the greater care people show on the רגל, Regel, it's
based on חז"ל's Chazal's desire to create a sense of unity among
the people on the רגל. Regel. But you know, it's an excellent
point. Right, here's something that clearly was handled before the רגל Regel
and nevertheless has that assumption. Yeah.
If the rabbis put these restrictions on about who can be trusted,
they can waive them.
Well, that's basically what I'm saying. Exactly. All right. Again, the question
to me was whether the rabbis were the ones that invented these
restrictions, but they're certainly the ones that are coming to modify them.
Okay. ואם אמר הפרשתי לתוכה רביעית קודש נאמן. Ve'im amar hifrasti letocha
revi'it kodesh ne'eman. And here's again the guy says he brings you
your barrel of wine and it's not during the times of the
pressing, so you know, I really can't take it now because I
can't assume that it's טהור. Tahor. Of course, if you were to
have separated out from that a little wine to make it for
נסכים Nesachim for קודש, Kodesh, then then I'd be able to believe
you about the wine because you always believe them about קודש Kodesh
and then I could believe you about the rest of the barrel
as well because it's all connected. So that works, okay, wink and
a nod. So the word says like this, תנן התם, Tnan hatam,
so we taught over
there, מודין בית שמאי לבית הלל שבודקין לעושי פסח ואין בודקין לאוכלי
תרומה, Modin Beit Shammai le-Beit Hillel shebodkin le-osei pesach ve-ein bodkin le-ochlei
terumah, that they agree that you check for people who are going
to bring their פסח, Pesach, Beit Shammai and Beit Hillel, but not
for people who are going to eat תרומה. Terumah. מאי בודקין, Mai
bodkin, what are you checking? So אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar
Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, מנפח אדם בית הפרס והולך. Menapeach adam beit
hapras veholech. So you basically have a field that has a קבר
Kever that was plowed over there and has possibly little bits of
bone in the field and that's considered rabbinically you're not allowed to
walk through that field or you'll become טמא. Tamei. And but you
have to cross through that field in order to get to ירושלים
Yerushalayim to bring your קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, or you have to
cross through that field I don't know to get home and eat
your תרומה, Terumah, whatever the case may be. So can you... is
there a way you can cross through that field? So they say
what you do is you like blow, it's sort of like what
you know like clearing the field for mines. So you blow the
area right in front of you so it would blow away any
little chips of bone on the surface and then you take a
step, then you blow the area in front of you and you
take a step. So you can do that if you have to
cross that field to eat your קרבן פסח Korban Pesach and you're
considered to be טהור.
Tahor. With what? Your your mouth.
You're walking across a field, blow,
step.
You better start... you better start עושי פסח. Osei Pesach.
Okay fine. All right.
This comes up
before
in... Yeah, this comes up this comes up a number of times.
Okay, so okay, so you can do that for פסח, Pesach, it's
more urgent for פסח Pesach obviously. If you don't bring your פסח
Pesach now you're going to blow it. And תרומה, Terumah, you know,
there's no urgency. So אוי, Oy, you know what I wasn't even
thinking about that, תרומה Terumah there's no urgency. Okay so you don't
allow this for תרומה. Terumah. Okay, רבי חייא בר אבא משמיה דעולא
אמר, Rebbi Chiya bar Abba mishmeih de-Ulla amar, בית הפרס שנידש טהור.
Beit hapras shenidash tahor.
Here's another assumption that you can make: עושי פסח. Osei Pesach. For
if you're doing your פסח Pesach and people have walked a path
through this field already and you can see that it's been trampled
down, right the earth has been like pressed down by people's walking,
then because it's been pre-tread, that somehow allows you to assume that
there are no real chips of bone that are left in that
path.
I don't know why being pre-tread makes you allows you to assume
that because it's not necessarily true that the people who walked cared
about טומאה, Tumah, you know, maybe they weren't כהנים Kohanim and whatever.
But right for some reason the fact that they tread makes us
assume that somehow the chips of bone have been dislodged off of
that tread.
Again only for עושי פסח? Osei Pesach?
If if for the purpose that you need to cross through that
field to bring your קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach.
But everyone else is bringing their קרבן פסח Korban Pesach too.
That's maybe. That's good maybe. Okay, so so if you're doing it
for פסח Pesach again you can be lenient either by blowing or
if there's a path that's been tread. לא העמידו דבריהם במקום כרת.
Lo he'emidu divreihem bimkom kareth. They did not put their position up
to prevent you from you know bringing a פסח Pesach which otherwise
you'd be liable כרת. Kareth. They didn't make their restrictions something that
that stands in the way of you possibly being liable כרת. Kareth.
אבל לאוכלי תרומה, Aval le-ochlei terumah, but to prevent you from eating
תרומה Terumah they did say, העמידו דבריהם במקום מיתה. He'emidu divreihem bimkom
mitah. That they they they had their position, you know they erected
their position, they kept it because to prevent you from eating תרומה
Terumah when you are טומאת מת, Tumat meis, which is a חיוב
מיתה. Chiyuv mitah. Now it's not exactly the same... it's a weird
parallel because by the פסח Pesach you're חייב כרת Chayav kareth if
you don't bring the פסח. Pesach. By תרומה Terumah you're חייב מיתה
בידי שמים Chayav mitah bidei shamayim if you eat the תרומה Terumah
when you're טמיא. Tameia. If you do it. So it's like funny.
It's like we wanted you to be able to do the the
פסח Pesach and you know otherwise you'd be חייב כרת Chayav kareth
so we had to move out of the way to let you
do the פסח Pesach we didn't want you to get כרת. Kareth.
But we are preventing you, you know in the case of the
תרומה, Terumah, not like now you're going to be חייב מיתה, Chayav
mitah, we're preventing you because that'll protect you from being חייב מיתה.
Chayav mitah. So it's the same point, we don't want you to
be חייב כרת Chayav kareth we don't want you to be חייב
מיתה, Chayav mitah, but it's a funny way it's structured in this
parallel.
Yes, but if the idea is one of נאמנות Ne'emanut as you
know that you... you relax the principles of נאמנות neemanus in general,
yes, then first of all I withdraw what I said before about
other people use that path, it would be any path, the idea
is that you rely on other people in general.
Right, so the reliability is very specific, meaning the reliability that we've
been talking about, right, is around- oh I see, you're saying because
פסח Pesach is a time of a רגל regel and so on.
Yeah, the גמרא Gemara let's see why the גמרא Gemara brings this
in. The גמרא Gemara has not brought this in to the assumption
that the reliability that we've been talking about about whether the food
is טמא tamei or not, translates into a general reliability about other
things. Like if you come into, I don't know, let's say it
happens to be the רגל regel and you know,
there're other types
of- you shouldn't make a distinction between תרומה truma and פסח Pesach
though, because for both of those things relate to טומאה, tumah, it's
not a question of is it חייב מיתה, chayav misah, מיתה בידי
שמים,
misah
b'yedei shamayim, or כרת kares or whatever, it's all about the נאמנות
neemanus on this kind of דרבנן. derabbanan.
Right,
but this is seen as more of an overrider or a leniency
less than a נאמנות, neemanus, right? You're the one blowing the path.
I mean, it's true the נידה niddah has to do with other
people, but I don't think the נידה niddah is because you assume
other people blew it, I think it just assumes that the natural
process of treading creates it, somehow dislodges the bone, though I don't
really understand that. But this really is not based on נאמנות, neemanus,
the first case clearly not, it's about blowing. This is פסח, Pesach,
do we allow this leniency, you know, this way of assuming that
this will address the טומאה tumah problems, it's a leniency, do we
allow it for this type of overriding concern? Yeah.
You're only חייב כרת chayav kares on פסח Pesach if you're within
a day of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Right. So but they don't mention-
That's a good point.
It's right. It's more like the category of חייב כרת. chayav kares.
You could also say you could be in פסח שני. Pesach Sheni.
Anyway, let's take a look. Let's try to figure out what the
גמרא Gemara is doing with it. איבעיא להו, Iba'u lehu, they ask
a question: בדק לפסחו מהו שיאכל בתרומתו Badak l'pischo mahu sheyochal b'trumaso?
This is where it becomes more- a little more relevant and we'll
see why it's bringing it in. So you went ahead and you
blew this path and walked through it and brought your קרבן פסח,
korban pesach, and now I want to eat my תרומה. truma. Okay,
so what can I do? Can I assume I'm also טהור tahor
for תרומה truma purposes? It'd be a little absurd to say I'm
טהור tahor to bring the קרבן פסח, korban pesach, but when I
want to eat תרומה truma I have to assume I'm טמא. tamei.
Okay, but that's the question they're asking. And now we're going to
see why it brought it in.
Would you compare כרת kares to מיתה בידי שמים? misah b'yedei shamayim?
What is- what- I understand, but it's also like can we- can
we give me a double- a different status for different things? So
let's take a look. So עולא אמר: Ulla amar: בדק לפסחו מותר
לאכול בתרומתו. Badak l'pischo mutar le'echol b'trumaso.
If you walked through this path by the blowing and you can
bring your פסח, Pesach, then you're טהור, tahor, you can eat your
תרומה. truma. רבא בר עולא אמר: Rabba bar Ulla amar: בדק לפסחו
אסור לאכול בתרומתו. Badak l'pischo assur le'echol b'trumaso. You can't. אמליה ההוא
סבא: Amlei hahu saba: לא תפלוג עליה דעולא, Lo tiflog alei d'Ulla,
so a certain elder said to רבא, Rabba, don't argue on עולא,
Ulla, who says if you're good for one it's good for the
other, דתנן כוותיה, d'tnan k'vosei, our משנה Mishnah supports him. Our משנה
Mishnah says: אם אמר הפרשתי לתוכה רביעית קודש נאמן. Im amar hifrashti
l'socha revi'is kodesh, ne'eman. That if he said that I took a
little- a little glass of wine out of that barrel and I
made it קודש, kodesh, then-
then he's believed about the whole barrel of wine since he's believed
on the little glass that's going to be for נסכים. nesachim. So
why don't we say no, you know, he's believed on the קודש
kodesh one, he's not believed on the rest of the barrel? But
we don't say that. אלמא מכדי הימן אקודש הימן נמי אתרומה. Alma
mi-di-heimen a-kodesh heimen nami a-truma. If you're believed for one, you're believed
for the other. הכא נמי מכדי הימן אפסח הימן נמי אתרומה, Hacha
nami mi-di-heimen a-Pesach heimen nami a-truma, here because this isn't you somebody
else is believed, since he is trusted that the blowing did a
sufficient job for the purposes of פסח, Pesach, הימן נמי אתרומה, heimen
nami a-truma, it also works for תרומה. truma. We're not going to
say you're- you know, the same person is טהור tahor for one
thing and טמא tamei for another, okay? In the same way the
same barrel of wine isn't going to be טהור tahor for taking
קודש kodesh out of it but טמא tamei for תרומה. truma. All
right, so that's- that's what that was brought in to illustrate those
things and there's no response. It makes a lot of sense. Okay.
קנקנין וקדשי שמן? Kan-kanin v'kadshei shemen? The last one. Okay, which is
barrels of wine and of oil, which are מדומעות, meduma'os, which normally
means some type of a mix of תרומה truma and חולין, chulin,
could also mean טבל, tevel, normally means a mix of תרומה truma
and חולין, chulin, they're believed on them at the time of the
גתות gissos and beforehand seventy days. Okay, so that's very bizarre. Why-
what is this status of מדומעת meduma'at and why does it have
a special status? Let's take a look. תנא אין נאמנין לא על
הקנקנין ולא על התרומה. Tana ein ne'emanin lo al hakan-kanin v'lo al
hatruma.
So they're not believed, not relating to the actual barrels themselves, the
jugs themselves, and not on the תרומה. truma. So what does this
mean? גמרא Gemara says like this: במאי? B'mai? What are we talking
about? אי קנקנין דקודש, Ei kan-kanin d'kodesh, if we're talking about like
jugs that have in it wine or oil that they sanctified, you
know, for בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash purposes, מיגו דהימן אקודש הימן נמי
אקנקנין. migu deheimen akodesh heimen nami akan-kanin.
It sort of goes to that thing we said before about it
all being interrelated, although we'll see later times when we don't say
that. But for now, if you're going to believe them that the
wine in the jug is טהור, tahor, they're going to believe them
that the jug is טהור. tahor. אלא אקנקנין דתרומה. Ela akan-kanin d'truma.
So they're not believed about the jugs of תרומה. truma. פשיטא, Pshita,
of course you're not believed if it's not a special- at the
שעת הגיתות, sh'at hagittot, if it's not the special time, of course
you're not believed on the jugs. השתא, Hashta, תרומה לא מהימן, truma
lo m'heman, if you're not believed on the תרומה truma itself, קנקנים
מהימן? kankanim m'heman? Why would you be believed on the jugs? So
what's the scenario where you're not believed on the jugs but he
says לא על הקנקנים ולא על התרומה? lo al hakankanim v'lo al
hatruma? So if it's not the תרומה, truma, presumably we're talking about
not the time of the גיתות. gittot. So of course not on
the קנקנים. kankanim. So when is there ever something special to be
said about the jugs?
אלא בריקנים דקודש, Ella b'reikanim d'kodesh, we're talking about empty jugs and
they're jugs you normally use to put your קודש kodesh wine and
oil in, but it happens to be right now it's empty, ובשאר
ימות השנה, u'v'sh'ar yemot hashana, and the rest of the year. So
the rest of the year, if I tell you this wine is
קודש, kodesh, it's טהור, tahor, you believe me even if I'm an
עם הארץ. am ha'aretz. Okay, and if I brought it in a
jug, you'd believe that the jug is טהור. tahor. That's what the
גמרא Gemara says, it's all, you can't say one without the other.
Okay, but if this is the jug that I normally use for
my קודש kodesh wine, right now it doesn't have קודש kodesh wine
in it and you're the חבר chaver and you want to borrow
my jug, and I say, "Sure, I'll tell you what, I'll even
let you use my jugs that I use for my קודש kodesh
wine, and you can use it and borrow it," you would have
to still take it to the מקווה mikvah because even though you
believe me that it's טהור tahor when the קודש kodesh wine was
in it, right now when it's only about the jug, you have
to assume it's טמא. tamei.
Okay, so that's
בריקנים דקודש b'reikanim d'kodesh ובשאר ימות השנה. u'v'sh'ar yemot hashana. That's when
you don't believe them about the jugs. Now, ובמלאים דתרומה ובשעת הגיתות.
u'v'mlei'im d'truma u'v'sh'at hagittot. Now, there could even be a time where
you believe them about the תרומה truma and not about the jugs,
and this is ironic. You go ahead and, right, you have a
jug filled with תרומה. truma. You believe me that the תרומה truma
is טהור. tahor. You believe me because it's the time of the
pressing, but you don't believe me about the jug. So you're going
to go ahead and I'm going to bring my, my,
you know, here it is, my jug of wine to you, the
כהן חבר, Kohen chaver, and give you my תרומה truma and it's
time of the גיתות gittot and you can believe me that it's
טהור, tahor, but you're going to say, "You know what? Why don't
you just pour it into my vessel here? You know, take your
vessel back." Okay, because you can't actually treat the vessel as טהור,
tahor, only the wine in it, which is of course bizarre. How
can the wine in it be טהור tahor and the vessel be
טמא? tamei? Okay, so that's just the fiction that we live with,
okay? Which is the גמרא Gemara initially assumed it's all got to
be the same, and here it says, "Not necessarily. We can believe
you on the wine without believing you on the vessel." Okay,
so if you take a look at רש"י, Rashi, just to see
רש"י Rashi spell this out, about 15 lines before the lines get
wide, ובמלאים דתרומה בשעת הגיתות שאף על פי שלא גזרו על תרומתן
בשעת הגיתות משום הפסד כהנים חברים. u'v'mlei'im d'truma b'sh'at hagittot she'af al
pi she'lo gazru al trumatan b'sh'at hagittot mishum hefsed kohanim chaverim. Now
here רש"י Rashi points out that if it's really just based on
the fact that everybody's being careful, then if everybody's really being careful
now, if you're going to believe them on the wine, you're going
to believe them on the jugs, right? So now רש"י Rashi gets
to the policy issue, and it's a little self-serving policy issue, so
let's take a look. He says, דלא גזרו על תרומתן בשעת הגיתות
מפני הפסד כהנים חברים שנמצא מפסידן מרוב תרומת ארץ ישראל. d'lo gazru
al trumatan b'sh'at hagittot mipnei hefsed kohanim chaverim shenimtza mafsidan mi'rov trumat
Eretz Yisrael.
So it's not just, oh, everybody is really careful during this period
of time. It's we've got to make it מותר mutar during this
period of time or all the כהנים Kohanim are going to lose
out on 90% of the תרומה. truma. So okay, now we'll believe
you. Okay, that's only for the wine, that's only for the stuff
that they need, but על הקנקנים לא הימינום דאין כהן חבר מקבל
מהן קנקנים עם התרומה אבל מערה הוא לכליהם. al hakankanim lo heiminum
d'ein kohen chaver mekabel mehen kankanim im hatruma aval me'areh hu l'cheleihem.
Okay,
so pour it into my thing. But here it's quite fascinating that
you, and we're going to see it again by the רגל, regel,
that there are certain policy considerations. Now the רגל regel is less
self-serving; the רגל regel is to create a sense of unity. This
is to ensure that the חברים chaverim get their share of the
תרומה. truma. Okay, and now presumably there are some facts to base
it on; people are more careful at the time of גיתות, gittot,
more careful at the time of the רגל. regel. But you know
what? At the end of the day, these are the policy considerations.
And the thing to make it understandable is that from the strict
הלכה halacha point of view, everybody would always be believed all the
time. All of this is just stringencies upon stringencies, so we're more
ready to waive it. But again, רש"י Rashi really makes clear the
policy issues here. Okay, so let's go back to the גמרא. Gemara.
So the גמרא Gemara says like
this, ובמלאים דתרומה ובשעת הגיתות. תנן והתנן התם כדי יין וכדי שמן
המדומעות. u'v'mlei'im d'truma u'v'sh'at hagittot. Tnan v'hatnan hatam kadei yayin v'kadei shemen
hameduma'ot. So barrels of wine, barrels of oil that are mixed, which
we still don't really know what that means.
מאי לאו מדומעות דתרומה? Mai lav meduma'ot d'truma? Doesn't it mean that
they are mixed with תרומה? truma? So meaning that they have תרומה
truma in it. And it says that the כדין kadim are also
believed. It says the barrels, right, or the pitchers of wine and
oil. Right, that's the point of the משנה, Mishna, not just the
wine and oil. The language is כדי יין וכדי שמן נאמנים עליהם.
kadei yayin v'kadei shemen ne'emanim aleihem. Right, so that's what the משנה
Mishna said. It said first of all, the wine you're believed בשעת
הגיתות, b'sh'at hagittot, and the כדין, kadim, the pitchers, you're believed even
70 days before. Okay, so here it's explicit; for God's sake, you're
believed on the. the pitchers even seventy days before, certainly at the
time of the גתות. gatzot. Why are you telling me you're not
believed on the on the vessels? So doesn't it mean that it
has תרומה terumah in it, and even anything that's going to have
תרומה terumah in it or going to be used for תרומה, terumah,
you're believed even seventy days before? So הגמרא ha-Gemara says, so אמר
דבי רבי חייא, amar devei Rabbi Chiyya, no, מדומעות דקדש. meduma'ot de-Kodesh.
No, it means stuff that you're going to use for קדש Kodesh
purposes. Okay, and that's why it's going you're believed on them even
about the big jugs themselves.
So the גמרא Gemara says, one minute, ומי איכא דמוע דקדש? u-mi
ika dimua de-Kodesh? When we talk about a mix for קדש, Kodesh,
a mix for תרומה, terumah, מאי טבל? mai tevel? So מדומעות לתרומה
meduma'ot le-terumah might mean that I'm using pitchers. It isn't yet the
time of pressing, but I'm using them for my grapes. My grapes
aren't yet תרומה, terumah, but they're מדומעות לתרומה meduma'ot le-terumah because they're
going to be תרומה's terumah going to be separated from them. So
meaning that would be a way of saying all the types of
vessels I'm going to be using for this stuff that תרומה's terumah
going to come out of, so the same way I'm believed about
the תרומה, terumah, I'm even believed about the vessels that I'm using
with the olives and the grapes that have the pre-תרומה terumah mixed
into them effectively because it's טבל. tevel. Okay, that makes a lot
of sense, but that would tell me that I'd be believed about
the vessels. But you said I'm not believed about the vessels. To
say okay, we're talking not about תרומה, terumah, we're talking about קדש.
Kodesh. So what does דמוע dimua mean in the context of קדש?
Kodesh? So the גמרא Gemara says, ומי איכא דמוע דקדש? u-mi ika
dimua de-Kodesh? אמר דבי רבי אלעאי, amar devei Rabbi Ilai, במטהרת טבלו
ליטול ממנו נסכים. be-metaheret tivlo litol mimenu nesakhim. Yes,
because what it means is is that I have declared my intention
that I am going to be taking wine for נסכים nesakhim out
of what we're going to be pressing, the wine we're going to
be pressing. So here we are, we're harvesting all the grapes, I
make an announcement, guys, I want everybody be super care- עם הארץ,
am ha-aretz, I want everyone to be super careful because we're anyway
careful, but besides let's be super careful because I'm going to be
using some of this wine to bring my נסכים nesakhim from. I've
declared my intention, so these grapes are seen to have potential or
like not potential like a pre, you know, separated
out קדש, Kodesh, and therefore because that's their status, you can even
believe the status of the vessels that are used, not just the
status of the wine. Okay, so that's a really hard read in
the משנה. Mishna. Let's just admit that the פשט pshat of the
משנה Mishna is that you're believed on the vessels more than the
wine. The wine you're only believed בשעת הגתות, be-sha'at ha-gatzot, and the
vessels you're believed even seventy days before. Why do you think by
the way you'd be believed in the vessels before you begin to
be believed about the wine?
You have to
prepare the vessels ahead of time. Okay, so that's the simple sense
of the משנה. Mishna. But since the גמרא Gemara says that you're
not believed on the vessels for תרומה, terumah, only on the wine,
only on the actual, you know, sort of food, it has to
go ahead and make it a special case of קדש, Kodesh, not
a case of תרומה. terumah. And now let's just look at this
idea that the belief of the of vessels begins seventy days before.
So קודם הגתות שבעים יום. kodem ha-gatzot shivim yom. אמר אביי, amar
Abaye, שמע
מינה, shema mina, we hear from this דינא הוא, dina hu, the
rule is or the practice
is
דאילויי אריסא למטרח
אגופנא de-iluiei arisa le-mitrach agufna seventy days before the actual time of
the harvest. It says belief seventy days before, means that the normal
practice is to start preparing everything already, that's a long time, like
two months before the actual period of the harvest. Okay, so that's
the issue of belief on the vessels as opposed to just the
wine, but given the גמרא Gemara that you're not believed on it,
we really highlight as רש''י Rashi points out the policy considerations that
are at play here in terms of believing people about the תרומה.
terumah.
Yes, the further we go in this, the more it seems like
this is bizarre תלמוד. Talmud. Yes, what is this idea that so
because you announce that what category is that because you announce that
I'm going to take קדש Kodesh out of this thing, it's like
what is this principle, it doesn't appear anywhere.
Right, I agree. I mean I made it a little simplified because
it says מטהר טבלו, metaher tavlo, which means like I'm actually going
through and keep saying trying to do some practice like, like, you
know, I'm not just stating it but I'm saying and let's be
really careful now that we dunk it in the מקווה, mikvah, you
know, we realize that we're going to be using it for קדש.
Kodesh. But still it's an ontology. I understand, yes, I agree, I
agree, it is. All right, so now next משנה Mishna and now
we're sort of coming into where we're circling in on where we
do away with these distinctions. So we have קדש Kodesh in general
in יהודה. Yehuda. We've got תרומה terumah at, at the time of
the pressing and maybe the and the issue of the vessels was
a little different. And now we get to places near ירושלים Yerushalayim
at all times of the year around this is about vessels, we're
now on vessels for a moment before we get back to food.
מן המודיעים ולפנים min ha-modi'in u-lifnim from מודיעים Modi'in which is a
place about it says fifteen מיל mil outside of ירושלים Yerushalayim which
is about fifteen kilometers, okay so which is a significant place, it's
like where you could get to ירושלים Yerushalayim in you know in
a day or in a half a day.
So it's in the immediate environs of
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Depending on the traffic you say. נאמנים על כלי חרס.
ne'emanin al kley cheres. that you are believed, עם הארץ am ha-aretz
*am haaretz* are believed that the pottery vessels are טהור tahor? *tahor*
at all times. Why is that? So we're going to say that
they did not make kilns in ירושלים Yerushalayim, *Yerushalayim* for making pottery
because that would have smelled up ירושלים Yerushalayim, *Yerushalayim* and even then
they had air pollution rules or whatever, so the kilns were always
outside of ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. Okay, which means you're putting them outside of
ירושלים *Yerushalayim*, so you're also putting them in the area where the
more likely, where the villagers and the more עמי הארץ amei ha-aretz,
*amei haaretz* are presumably. And therefore you've got to come up with
a more lenient policy to believe people for the sake of the
people in ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. You've got to be able to believe the
people out in the outside of ירושלים *Yerushalayim* who are the ones
making the pottery, okay? So there we actually again a policy consideration,
we are going to believe them for the, because people need pottery
vessels and they're not able to make them themselves. They're being made
on the outskirts, you know, in ירושלים *Yerushalayim*, in the industrial area
or whatever, and that's where you'll have the עם הארץ am ha-aretz
*am haaretz* who are making it. So if you look at רש"י
Rashi *Rashi* again in terms of the policy, five lines down in
the wide lines, רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says: ולפיכך האמינו שלא לגזור עליהם
שהן גזרה דלית ציבור שאין רוב ציבור יכולים לעמוד בה *Ulefikach heeminu
shelo ligzor aleihem shehen gezeira d'leit tzibbur sheein rov tzibbur yecholim laamod
bah*. If you told people you couldn't trust the people who are
making the pottery vessels, nobody would be able to live with that.
You need to be able to buy pottery vessels. All right, so
we'll trust them about the pottery vessels, okay? Now, we're going to
see later that it's about like the small and the thin vessels,
not the big heavy ones, because the small and the thin ones
are the more daily use vessels where there's more of a need,
and therefore they gave them, you know, blanket believability. מן המודעין ולחוץ
*Min haModiin velachutz*, if however it's from מודעין *Modiin* away from ירושלים
*Yerushalayim*, אין נאמנים *ein neemanin*, they're not believed. כיצד *Keitzad*, how is
this? הקדר שהוא מוכר קדירות *Hakadar shehu mocher kadeirot*, you have a,
you know, a jug merchant who's selling his jugs, נכנס לפנים מן
המודעין *nichnas lifnim miModiin*, you're going to like this Dov because this
is both of you Dovs, I guess, whatever, anyway, because this is
the absurdity that it's telling you explicitly: the same guy, here's the
guy with the jugs on his back, with his donkey, whatever, his
wagon filled with jugs. נכנס לפנים מן המודעין *Nichnas lifnim miModiin*,
he's now, you find and you bump into him and he's in
from מודעין *Modiin* towards ירושלים *Yerushalayim*, הוא הקדר והן
הקדירות והן הלוקחים *hu hakadar vehen hakdeirot vehen halokechim*, נאמן *neeman*, you
can buy it. יצא Yatza, *Yatza*, if the same guy with the
same jugs and the same sellers you happen to bump into him
outside of מודעין *Modiin*, אינו נאמן eino ne'eman, *eino neeman*, he's not
believed. So here the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* spells out to you the
pure formalism of this. We gotta have rules and you know, these
are the rules, you can't go ahead and check every case individually,
these are the rules and this is how it works, okay?
Same as a lawful
trap
on 47th street?
Exactly. Okay, תנא *tana*: מודעין פעמים כלפנים ופעמים כלחוץ *Modiin pe'amim kelifnim
ufe'amim kelachutz*. How about מודעין *Modiin* itself, right? You said from inside
מודעין *Modiin* and outside מודעין *Modiin*. What about מודעין *Modiin* itself? What's
its status? So sometimes it's like the inside and sometimes the outside.
This is going to get really weird. כיצד *Keitzad*, how is this
possible? קדר kadar יוצא וחבר נכנס *Kadar yotze vechaver nichnas*, כלפנים *kelifnim*.
If the jug merchant is going away from ירושלים *Yerushalayim* and the
חבר chaver *chaver* is going towards ירושלים *Yerushalayim*, so this is the
last opportunity, right? Here's ירושלים *Yerushalayim*,
here's מודעין *Modiin*,
okay, מודעין *Modiin*. Okay, now, if you are the חבר chaver *chaver*
and you're heading away from ירושלים *Yerushalayim* and he's the קדר *kadar*
and he's planning on going towards...
Oh, it's the other way around first?
קדר יוצא *Kadar yotze*, thank you.
So you're the קדר *kadar* and you're in מודעין *Modiin* and you're
going away and this guy is the חבר *chaver* and he's heading
towards ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. So this is the last opportunity the חבר *chaver*
will have to buy the jugs from the קדר *kadar*, right? Because
he's going away and he's going towards. Okay, so since it's the
last opportunity that he'll have to do it, we'll consider it like
it's towards ירושלים *Yerushalayim* and he can buy the jugs, okay? קדר
יוצא וחבר נכנס *Kadar yotze vechaver nichnas*, כלפנים *kelifnim*. שניהם נכנסין *Sheneihem
nichnasin*, if they're both on the way towards ירושלים *Yerushalayim*, so don't
buy it in מודעין *Modiin*. Wait till you get, you know, inside,
you know, within מודעין *Modiin*, wait till you get, you know, past,
you know, within the inside. This is לפנים *lifnim*. Okay,
so wait till you and this is לחוץ *lachutz*. So wait till
you get into the לפנים *lifnim* section. Don't do it in מודעין
*Modiin*, get into the לפנים *lifnim* section, okay? Because you're both going
in that direction anyway. Okay, just because you're both going in that
direction, I don't know how it means they're necessarily traveling together, but
okay. שניהם נכנסין או שניהם יוצאין *Sheneihem nichnasin o sheneihem yotze'in*, כלחוץ
*kelachutz*. The interesting thing though also is that if you're both heading
out, it's also כלחוץ *kelachutz*. But that makes a little bit of
sense since you're on your way out even when you're in מודעין
*Modiin*, we look at you more as away from ירושלים *Yerushalayim* than
we look at you as towards ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. Okay, אמר אביי *amar
Abaye*: אף אנן נמי תנינא *af anan nami tanina*. This can also
be inferred from the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*, which is going to be
interesting because we didn't see any of this in the משנה mishna
*Mishnah*. Let's take a look. הקדר שמכר *Hakadar shemachar* הקדר שמוכר הקדרות
ונכנס לפנים מן המודיעין. It says the jug seller who is selling
them and is now found inside of מודיעין, Modiin, he's believed. טעמא
דלפנים מן המודיעין, Taama delifnim min ha-Modiin, that means that only inside
of מודיעין Modiin he's believed. המודיעין גופא, Ha-Modiin gufa, in מודיעין Modiin
itself, לא מהימן, lo meiman, he's not believed. אימא סיפא, Eima seifa,
let's look at the end. יצא, if he leaves away outside of
מודיעין, Modiin, אינו נאמן, he's not believed. המודיעין גופא נאמן, Ha-Modiin gufa
ne'eman, it sounds like in מודיעין Modiin he is believed. Right? The
משנה mishna. is not clear about מודיעין. Modiin. So rather than saying
the משנה is being clear, we're going to reconcile it. אלא לאו,
Ela lav, it must depend on the case. שמע מינה, Shma mina,
כאן בקדר יוצא וחבר נכנס, kan bekadar yotze vechaver nichnas, if the
קדר is going away and the חבר is going in, then מודיעין
Modiin is like it's inside and he is believed. כאן בשניהם יוצאים
או שניהם נכנסים, kan beshneihem yotzim o shneihem nichnasim, if they're both
leaving and they're or they're both going, then it's considered on the
outside. And the גמרא Gemara accepts that. שמע מינה. Shma mina. Oh,
that's a good inference. I mean, you could have speculated on a
dozen other ways of distinguishing, but that's the גמרא'ס Gemara's preferred to
read that in. Okay, now we have a qualification of why believing
them on these jugs—on these vessels—I mentioned this already. תנא נאמנין על
כלי חרס הדקים לקודש. Tana ne'emanin al klei cheres hadakim lekodesh. They're
believed on the thin ones, on the—like—the small ones to use them
for לקודש lekodesh purposes. So this is a double qualification. Okay,
basically they're the small ones, not the large ones, because the small
ones are the ones that are more in demand and therefore we
need to have greater leniencies. Okay, and we'll see a little bit
more about that. But it also says that they're believed on it
לקודש, lekodesh, which is not totally clear what it means. רש"י Rashi
doesn't really fully explicate that. Does it mean even if you want
to use it for קודש kodesh purposes, or only if they claim
that this is, you know, because it's for קודש, kodesh, that gives
them extra believability like we saw a little bit before? Not exactly
clear. But okay, let's take a look. But the key thing that
it's interesting—but certainly the idea that it's only on the small ones,
on the thin and the small ones.
אמר ריש לקיש והוא שניטלין בידו אחת. Amar Resh Lakish vehu shenitlin
beyado achat. They have to be so small that you can basically
carry them with one hand. ורבי יוחנן אמר אפילו שאין ניטלין בידו
אחת, Verabi Yochanan amar afilu she-ein nitlin beyado achat, even if you
basically need to use two hands. Maybe they're thin, they're big but
they're thin. אמר ריש לקיש לא שנו אלא ריקנים אבל מלאים לא.
Amar Resh Lakish lo shanu ela rekanim aval mle'im lo. It's only
if they're empty. If they're full, then not. Normally before we saw
that full was better because you could be believed on what's inside.
But here we'll be dealing with a case where maybe
it's not true—you know—they're saying—let's say the inside is תרומה—let's terumah say
the inside is חולין. chullin. So they're not believed about חולין chullin
wine. They're, you know, they're not believed about תרומה terumah wine not
during the time of the press. So basically if they're selling you
the jug with the wine in it, but it's not תרומה, terumah,
it's not קודש, kodesh, it's just חולין, chullin, you have to assume
the wine is טמא. tamei. So when you're buying the wine and
assume the wine is טמא, tamei, still assume the jug is טהור?
tahor It's like the reverse of what we had before, right? Before
you bought the wine that was תרומה terumah at the time of
the—of the pressing, you assumed the wine was טהור tahor? but you
had to assume the jug was טמא. tamei. Here, because it's a
special believability about the vessels—it's about pottery vessels from
מודיעין Modiin ולפנים—so velifnim we're talking the believability here is specific to
the vessels. What if you have to assume the wine is טמא
tamei based on the normal rules? Would you be still allowed to
assume that the vessel is טהור? tahor Okay, so ריש לקיש Resh
Lakish says it's only if they're empty. If they're full and you
have to assume that the stuff in it is טמא, tamei, so
you have to assume that the vessel is טמא tamei too.
ורבי יוחנן אמר אפילו מלאים, Verabi Yochanan amar afilu mle'im, even if
it's full. It's the same way that it was possible before to—to
say the contradictory idea, right? Before we said the תרומה terumah wine
was טהור tahor. and the vessel was טמא. tamei. Here we're saying
the wine is טמא tamei and the vessel's טהור. tahor. Okay. So
it says, ואפילו אפיקורסותו לתוכו, va-afilu apikorsuto letocho, even if your heresy
is in it.
No, that's not what it means.
אפיקורסותו Apikorsuto basically means like your undershirt or something, but nobody exactly
knows what the point of saying of saying that is other than
like just I don't know some type of a throwaway line. רש"י
Rashi basically says even like filled with חולין chullin wine. How that's
אפיקורסותו apikorsuto means that I don't know. ואמר רבא, Ve-amar Rava, but
anyway, even though the wine is טמא, tamei, the vessel is טהור.
tahor ואמר רבא ומודי רבי יוחנן במשקין עצמן שהן טמאין. Ve-amar Rava
u-modeh Rabi Yochanan bemashkin atzman she-hen tme'in. He's not claiming that if
it's full that you—because the vessel is טהור—the tahor. liquid is טהור.
tahor. No. He's saying I can see the liquid is טמא, tamei,
it's חולין, chullin, he's not believed on חולין, chullin, or it's תרומה
terumah not at the time
of the גיתות. gitot. So—so the, yeah, the liquid is טמא, tamei,
but nevertheless the vessel's טהור. tahor, We're going to live with this
contradiction. ואל תתמה, Ve-al titma, don't be astounded, right? Because obviously you
should be astounded, but don't be astounded. שהרי לוגין מלאין משקין, Sheharei
lugin mle'in mashkin, if you have, you know, pitchers or whatever filled
with liquid, לוגין טמא טומאת שבעה ומשקין טהורין, lugin tamei tumat shiva
u-mashkin tehorin, you can have the pitchers which are טמא tamei for
seven days because of מת met and the liquid's טהורין. tehorin. You
will remember we had this before that בית הלל ובית שמאי, Beit
Hillel ve-Beit Shammai,
right, the case about the house, right, that had the dead body
in it, right, and you had the כלי חרס... kli cheres... here
and the second thing, right, remember that, and you had, you know,
something and you had food there or whatever, anyway, so basically what
we said was the טומאה tumah goes through because you have to
assume כלי חרס kli cheres is טמא, tame, but the עם הארץ
am ha-aretz. won't believe, won't listen to us and believe us. So
we'll say for the stuff that we're not going to handle, that
only the עם הארץ am ha-aretz will eat, like the food, that's
טמא טומאת שבעה. tame tumat shiva. The stuff we have to, I'm
sorry, that's טהור, tahor. excuse me, because it's not going to affect
us anyway. The stuff we might use, like the vessels, that's going
to be טמא טומאת שבעה. tame tumat shiva. So that's what it
says, we had the same thing: the vessel could be טמא טומאת
שבעה tame tumat shiva and the food inside of it could be
טהור. tahor. So here too, the reverse: the wine could be טמא
tame and the vessel could be טהור. Okay, so we're getting into
some crazy ideas, but what we're actually, but the larger theme that
we're seeing is the way the policy issues about making sure כהנים
חברים kohanim chaverim get their fair share of the תרומה, terumah, making
sure people have pottery vessels, right, making sure that people don't run
off the דרך derech and abandon us because they don't have access
to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash because of all these various types
of considerations, we're going to believe people even if normally we wouldn't
believe them, or because of stringencies we wouldn't believe them. And we're
going to finally get to the idea where this is all leading,
which is in the רגל Regel is the big policy consideration that
everybody's believed about everything. Okay, let's just try to read one more
section here, see if we can get this one quickly.
הגבאים שנכנסו, Hagabbaim shenichnesu, tax collectors that came into the house, לתוך
הבית, letoch habayit, and they came to maybe seize some property because
you're behind in your taxes, וכן הגנבים שהחזירו את הכלים, vechen haganavim
shehecheziru et hakelim, or let's say thieves came into your house and
then they stole stuff but then they did תשובה, teshuva, that's appropriate
for ערב יום כיפור, Erev Yom Kippur, and they're returning the stuff,
נאמנים לומר לא נגענו. ne'emanim lomar lo naganu. So they're, the tax
collectors are believed to say, you know, we didn't touch these vessels,
maybe we touched these, we didn't touch those, you believe them. And
the ones they didn't touch, you assume the tax collectors are the
עם הארץ. am ha'aretz Remember, Jesus is eating with the tax collectors?
There's the עמי הארץ, the people you don't eat with, the people
you keep separate from. Okay, anyway, but they're believed to say what
they touched and what they didn't touch so you don't have to
worry about the stuff that they touched. Similarly, the גנב ganav comes
and he returns the vessels, A, maybe you believe him that even
though I stole these vessels, I didn't touch the other ones, or
maybe even the vessels he's returning, he's believed to say he didn't
touch let's say the wine inside of it. Let's say it's a
pottery vessel that if you don't touch the inside, you don't make
it טמא. tame. So they're all believed, amazing, even the people, גנבים,
ganavim, tax collectors, people you generally wouldn't believe about this stuff, they
are believed. ובירושלים נאמנים על הקודש. U'v'Yerushalayim ne'emanim al hakodesh. And in
ירושלים, people, now this is no longer tax collectors, in ירושלים, people
are believed about קודש. kodesh. I mean, we also saw in יהודה
Yehuda they're believed about קודש. kodesh. And here's the point that I
keep, I've been telling you, ובשעת הרגל, u'v'shat ha-regel, at the time
of the רגל, Regel, אף על התרומה, af al haterumah, everybody is
believed even on תרומה. terumah. Okay, so the thing about שעת הרגל
shat ha-regel everybody believed is like the big hugest thing about unifying
the people, but the tax collector thing comes first. Let's just read
the גמרא Gemara on the tax collectors. Let's take a look. ורמינהי,
U'reminhi,
הגבאים שנכנסו, hagabbaim shenichnesu, we have a ברייתא braita that says the,
a משנה that says the opposite: tax collectors came into the house,
לתוך הבית, letoch habayit, כולו טמא, kulo tame, everything is טמא. tame.
Says לא קשיא: lo kashya: הא דנכרי בהדיה והא דלא נכרי בהדיה.
ha d'nochri bahadei v'ha d'la nochri bahadei. Is there a נכרי nochri
with them or not? If there's a נכרי nochri with them and
he's supervising or whatever, they're going to have to inspect all of
your various vessels, you know, so therefore you have to assume they
touched everything and they're not going to, you can't believe them. But
if there's, if there's not a נכרי nochri with them, then they'll
be more careful. דתנן: D'tanan: אם יש נכרי עמהם, im yesh nochri
imahem, if there is a נכרי nochri with them, נאמנים לומר לא
נכנסנו, ne'emanim lomar lo nichnasnu, they can say we didn't go into
the house because, you know, they wouldn't make it up. אבל אין
נאמנים לומר נכנסנו אבל לא נגענו, aval ein ne'emanim lomar nichnasnu aval
lo naganu, they can't say we went in and we did not
touch. Right? רש"י Rashi explains why. Because רש"י Rashi says,
אין נאמנים לומר לא נגענו דמירתת אם לא יחפשו כל הבית. ein
ne'emanim lomar lo naganu d'mirtat im lo yechapsu kol habayit. Not because
the נכרי nochri will make them lie to say they didn't touch,
but because you have to assume if there was a נכרי nochri
there, they inspected everything because they didn't want to get in trouble,
you know, with their supervisor. Right, basically. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says, אבל לא נגענו אבל אין נאמנים לומר, where is
it, הא אבל אין נאמנים לומר נכנסנו ולא נגענו. וכי איכא נכרי
בהדיה מאי הוי? Vechi ika nochri bahadei mai havei? Who cares? Why
does it make a difference? רבי יוחנן ורבי אלעזר. Rabbi Yochanan v'Rabbi
Eleazar. חד אמר אימת נכרי עליהם, chad amar eimat nochri aleihem, they're
afraid of him, וחד אמר אימת מלכות עליהם, v'chad amar eimat malchut
aleihem, he represents the government and they're afraid he's going to report
to the government that they didn't do a good enough job. So
מאי בינייהו? mai beinaihu? Who cares if it's him or, or him
reporting? איכא בינייהו נכרי שאינו חשוב, Ika beinaihu nochri she'eino chashuv, that
he's not such an important guy, so they're not afraid of him.
But are they still have to afraid that he might report on
them? Okay.
So that's just another עם הארץ who's supervising them?
So that presumably would, they then they wouldn't have to do, they
wouldn't have to check out everything. You know, it's their fellow Jew,
they'll be a little easygoing, they won't do a, and you know,
but a נכרי, nochri, he's going to make them, you know, do.
Let's just read the one thing about the גנבים. ganavim.
Take a look at the next משנה. We have ten minutes. We
do?
I it says 8:30 here. 8:28. וכן הגנבים שהחזירו את הכלים. vechen
haganavim shehecheziru et hakelim. So the גמרא Gemara says... It's רמינו Ram'inu
that you believe in גנבים ganavim that are returning things? You're right,
my thing is fast. רמינו. Ram'inu. I'll ask you on this: הגנבים
שנכנסו לתוך הבית אינו טמא אלא מקום דריסת רגלי הגנבים. Haganavim shenichnesu
l'toch habayit eino tamei ela mekom drisat raglei haganavim. It's only טמא
tamei where they're walking, but so that's not exactly clear what the
question is. Why is that a problem? It's only where they walked
is טמא. tamei. But רש"י Rashi assumes that the question is, if
where they walk you have to assume is טמא, tamei, then maybe
you have to assume that the vessels that they handled are טמא
tamei and you can't, they can't tell you they didn't touch the
stuff inside the vessel. Not so clear what the question is. Let's
see what the answer is. אמר רב פנחס משמיה דרב או משמיה
דרבא. Amar Rav Pinchas mishmei deRav o mishmei deRava. Anyway, it's an
important answer for ערב יום כיפור. erev Yom Kippur. כשהעשו תשובה. K'she'asu
teshuvah. Oh, when they did תשובה, teshuvah, then because they're returning the
vessels, then you believe them. Because they're doing, they're returning the vessels,
they're doing תשובה. teshuvah. But when they didn't do תשובה, teshuvah, then
you have to assume that wherever they might have touched was טמא.
tamei. Okay, דיקא נמי דקתני שהחזירו את הכלים. Deika nami dektani shehecheziru
et hakelim. It says שהחזירו את הכלים. shehecheziru et hakelim. שמע מינה.
Shma mina. That is a good point. Okay, so now the question
here is, by the way, what isn't explored is why do you
believe these people? Like you normally don't believe them about things like
קודש kodesh and תרומה terumah and so on. Why do you believe
them? Whatever. So רש"י says it's only about קודש, kodesh, and it
goes back to the point that you believe עם הארץ about קודש.
kodesh. תוספות Tosafot says it's even about תרומה. terumah. And maybe there's
a difference between believing them on their own stuff and believing them
on your stuff. Like maybe, you know, for my own stuff, I
understand that you're a חבר and I'm not going to tell you,
you know, and I know you care about this or whatever, I'm
not going to tell you that I did or didn't touch it
when it's not true, it's your stuff. But my stuff, you know,
what I believe I've done correctly with my stuff, maybe I'll, you
know, interpret those facts differently than if you're asking me about how
I handled your stuff. And it's true, you know, I mean sometimes
it's the reverse. How do we handle other people's property as opposed
to how we handle our own?
Sometimes some people are more careful with other people's property, other people
are more sloppy with other people's property. But that is interesting, but
רש"י limits it to קודש. kodesh. Okay, you know what? I am
going to end here because we will start after יום כיפור Yom
Kippur and we'll read how all ישראל Yisrael comes together על הרגל
al haregel as a proper lead-in to סוכות. Sukkot. So that's what
we're going to pick up with מוצאי יום כיפור. motzaei Yom Kippur.
Everybody should have an easy and a meaningful fast.
Normal time on Sunday. Normal time on Sunday.